Guide to the Ramón Gómez de la Serna Papers [Guía a los materiales de Ramón Gómez de la Serna], 1906-1967 SC.1967.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Writings [Escritos], II.
  - Biographies [Biografías], 4.
    - José Gutiérrez Solana
      - "Los carnavales y la pintura de Gutierrez Solana," Typescript by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 16)
      - "Éxito en América," Typescript by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 17)
      - "Gutierrez Solana: Sus agua fuertes," Typescript by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 18)
      - "El torero Lechuga," Typescript by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 19)
      - "Visita al hermano," Typescript by Ramón (Box 36, Folder 20)
      - Unidentified Typescript Fragment (Box 36, Folder 21)
      - Unidentified Manuscript Fragment (Box 36, Folder 22)
      - Article Clippings about Solana by Ramón and Others, 1955 and undated (Box 36, Folder 23)
      - Clippings and Photographs of Solana, His Art, and Related, 1907 and undated (Box 36, Folder 24)
    - "Azorín"
      José Augusto Trinidad Martínez Ruíz, also known as Azorín (June 8, 1873, Monòver - March 2, 1967), was a Spanish writer and literary critic. This folder contains mainly portrait clippings of Azorín and photographs relating to the author.
      José Augusto Trinidad Martínez Ruíz, también conocido como Azorín (8 de junio de 1873, Monòver - 2 de marzo de 1967), fue un escritor y crítico literario español. Esta carpeta contiene principalmente recortes de retratos de Azorín y fotografías relacionadas con el autor.
      - "Azorín: Ultimas notas y grafica" (Box 36, Folder 25)
    - Juan Bautista Martínez del Mazo
      Juan Bautista Martínez del Mazo (ca.1612 – February 10, 1667) was a Spanish Baroque portrait and landscape painter, the most distinguished of the followers of Velázquez, whose style he imitated more closely than any other artist. This folder contains clippings of an encyclopedia entry on the painter and several clippings of his works.
      Juan Bautista Martínez del Mazo (ca.1612 - 10 de febrero de 1667) fue un retratista y paisajista barroco español, el más distinguido de los seguidores de Velázquez, cuyo estilo imitaba más de cerca que cualquier otro artista. Esta carpeta contiene recortes de una entrada de la enciclopedia sobre el pintor y varios recortes de sus obras.
      - "Del Mazo" (Box 36, Folder 26)
    - Norah Borges
      This section contains a three-page, annotated typescript that was located in the beginning of the published biography of Norah Borges authored by Ramón.
      Esta sección contiene un mecanografiado anotado de tres páginas que se encuentra al comienzo de la biografía publicada de Norah Borges, hecha por Ramón.
      - "Norah Borges": Typescript (Box 36, Folder 27)
  - "Diccionario Manual", 5.
    These cards appear to be a private working thesaurus compiled by Ramón showing his interest in and concern for language, and the picturesque and expressive richness of words. Usually, each card has on one side handwritten word lists and on the other pasted clippings of sayings, anecdotes, brief articles, or similar published texts.
    Estas tarjetas parecen ser un tesauro de trabajo privado compilado por Ramón que muestra su interés y preocupación por el lenguaje y la riqueza pintoresca y expresiva de las palabras. Por lo general, cada tarjeta tiene en un lado listas de palabras escritas a mano y en el otro recortes pegados de dichos, anécdotas, artículos breves o textos similares publicados.
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Dictionary Cards, 2-sided (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - Dictionary Cards, 1-sided (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - Dictionary Cards, 1-sided (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - Dictionary Cards, 1-sided (Box 37, Folder 17)
    - Dictionary Cards, 1-sided (Box 37, Folder 18)
    - Dictionary Cards, 1-sided (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Dictionary Cards, 1-sided (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Dictionary Cards, 1-sided (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Dictionary Cards, 1-sided (Box 38, Folder 4)
- Correspondence [Correspondencia], III.
  This series contains correspondence, mainly from the Spanish playwright and novelist Enrique Jardiel Poncela, and letters from Ramón to Luis de Olarra and Ernesto Bustamante. Poncela supplies Ramón with his enthusiastic impressions of nationalist Spain during and after the Civil War. From the transcripts of the letters to Olarra, whose brother was the director of Espasa Calpe, we learn a few bibliographical and publishing details and some personal confidences. The letters to the Argentinian poet Bustamante reveal more bibliographical and biographical details while inquiring about books necessary for his work. The remaining less substantial letters are from Jules Supervielle, Manuel de Falla, Jean Cocteau, Camilo José Cela, José Calvo Sotelo, Marqués de Luca de Tena, Ortega y Gasset, Alberto Hidalgo, and Manuel Gálvez. In addition, there are four poems dedicated to Ramón from Latin American poets and the original of the letter from Miguel Moya about "El Torero Caracho," which is referred to in "Automoribundie."
  Esta serie contiene correspondencia, principalmente del dramaturgo y novelista español Enrique Jardiel Poncela, y cartas de Ramón a Luis de Olarra y Ernesto Bustamante. Poncela proporciona a Ramón sus impresiones entusiastas de la España nacionalista durante y después de la Guerra Civil. De las transcripciones de las cartas a Olarra, cuyo hermano era el director de Espasa Calpe, aprendemos algunos detalles bibliográficos y editoriales y algunas confidencias personales. Las cartas al poeta argentino Bustamante revelan más detalles bibliográficos y biográficos al preguntar sobre los libros necesarios para su trabajo. Las restantes y menos sustanciales cartas son de Jules Supervielle, Manuel de Falla, Jean Cocteau, Camilo José Cela, José Calvo Sotelo, Marqués de Luca de Tena, Ortega y Gasset, Alberto Hidalgo y Manuel Gálvez. Además, hay cuatro poemas dedicados a Ramón de poetas latinoamericanos y el original de la carta de Miguel Moya sobre "El Torero Caracho", al que se hace referencia en "Automoribundie".
  - Transcription of Selected Items from Box 39 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to Ernesto Bustamante, 1943-1960 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence to Ernesto Bustamante, undated (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence to Luís de Olarra, Transcripts, 1952-1961 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Ramón, 1941-1962 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to Ramón, 1926-1961 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to Rodolfo Cardona from Teodoro Llanos Alvarez, 1963 (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Drawings of Ramón (Box 39, Folder 8)
- Clippings and Some Notes about International Authors, Artists, Intellectuals, and Artwork [Recortes y algunas notas sobre autores internacionales, artistas, intelectuales y obras de arte], IV.
  This series comprises article and some graphical clippings from newspapers and magazines on a variety of authors, artists, and intellectuals from countries such as United States, Great Britain, Ireland, and France. Most of the material is undated but an approximate date-range would probably fall between the 1930s to the late 1950s. A few of Ramón's handwritten notes are interspersed among the clippings. It appears that he has compiled these clippings for inspiration, personal interest, or project-related work.
  Esta serie comprende artículos y algunos recortes gráficos de periódicos y revistas sobre una variedad de autores, artistas e intelectuales de países como Estados Unidos, Gran Bretaña, Irlanda y Francia. La mayor parte del material no tiene fecha, pero un intervalo de fechas aproximado probablemente caería entre la década de 1930 y finales de la década de 1950. Algunas de las notas escritas a mano de Ramón se intercalan entre los recortes. Parece que ha compilado estos recortes para inspiración, interés personal o trabajo relacionado con proyectos.
  - Clippings on US American Authors (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Clippings on US American Authors, 1937-1952 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American Authors, 1937-1958 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Clippings on US American and British Authors, 1948-1951 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Clippings on US American Authors (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American Authors (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Clippings on Mostly British and Irish Authors (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Clippings on British and Irish Authors (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Clippings on US American and British Authors (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - Clippings on Mostly US and British Authors (Box 40, Folder 10)
  - Clippings on Mostly British Authors (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - Clippings on Mostly British Authors (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - Clippings on Mostly British Authors (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - Clippings on US American Artists and Intellectuals (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Clippings and Notes on US American Artists (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Clippings on US American Artists and Theatre (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Clippings on US American Authors (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Clippings on US American and British Authors (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Clippings on US American Author Mark Twain (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Clippings on British Author Charles Dickens (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Clippings on US American and British Authors (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American, British, and Irish Authors, Artists, and Scientists (Box 41, Folder 9)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American Authors, Artitsts, and Intellectuals (Box 41, Folder 10)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American and British Authors, Artists, and Performers (Box 41, Folder 11)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American and British Authors (Box 41, Folder 12)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American and British Authors (Box 41, Folder 13)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American and British Authors (Box 41, Folder 14)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American and British Authors (Box 41, Folder 15)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American Authors (Box 41, Folder 16)
  - Clippings on Mostly US American and British Authors (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Clippings on Mostly British Authors (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Clippings on Mostly British and Irish Authors (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Clippings on Mostly British Authors (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Clippings and Ramón's Notes on H.G. Wells (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Clippings on Mostly British and French Authors (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Clippings on Mostly British Authors (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors and Artists (Box 42, Folder 11)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors (Box 42, Folder 12)
  - Clippings on French Poet Francis Jammes (Box 42, Folder 13)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors (Box 42, Folder 14)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors (Box 42, Folder 15)
  - Clippings on Mostly German, Russian, and Scandinavian Authors, Artitsts, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Clippings on Mostly German, Russian, and Scandinavian Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Clippings on Mostly German and Russian Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Clippings on Mostly Russian, German, and Scandinavian Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Clippings on French Author André Gide (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - Clippings on French Author François Mauriac, 1952 and undated (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 11)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 12)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 13)
  - Clippings on French Poet and Essayist Léon-Paul Fargue (Box 43, Folder 14)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 43, Folder 15)
  - Clippings on French Novelist and Playwright Honoré de Balzac (Box 43, Folder 16)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors (Box 43, Folder 17)
  - Clippings on French and Italian Authors and Artists (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Clippings on Italian Poet and Writer Ada Negri (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Clippings on Italian Authors and Artists (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Clippings on Italian Authors and Artists (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Clippings on Mostly Italian Authors and Artists (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Clippings on Mostly Italian Authors and Artists (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Clippings on Italian Author and Poet Giovanni Boccaccio (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Clippings on Mostly French, German, and Austrian Authors, Artists, and Intellectuals (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors and Artists (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - Clippings on Mostly French Authors and Artists (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - Clippings on International Authors and Artists (Box 44, Folder 13)
  - Imagage Clippings and Photographs on Mostly Authors, Artists, and Artworks (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - "Imágenes de Leda," Clippings and Notes (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - "Angeles," Clippings on Angels (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - "Tango," Notes and Clippings (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Clippings Authored by or About Ramón (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Clippings on Ramón's Life and Work Postmortem, 1966-1967 and undated (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Clippings on Ramón's Life and Work, Mostly Postmortem, 1960, 1966-1968 (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - Clippings on Ramón's Death and Remembrance, 1967-1968 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Banquet Announcements Honoring Ramón, 1966-1968 (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - Caricatures of Authors and Artists (Fernand Divoire, Jean Borlin, and Others) (Box 45, Folder 10)
  - "Poets on Poetry," Mimeograph by Unknown Author (Box 45, Folder 11)
  - "Lenormand en el teatro. Nota y selección por Luisa Sofovich." (Box 45, Folder 12)